Guide to the Chinese Gaming Counters Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Gaming Counters with Identified or Attributed Provenance, circa 1700-circa 1840; Series I; 182
  - Elphinstone family, Elphinstone, Stirling, Scotland
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lady from the middle well attired proper holding in her dexter hand a tower and in her sinister hand a laurel branch on a torse and above the monogram "CE" and flanked by flowers., circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Fearon family, Sussex, England
    Possibly James P. Fearon, captain of the East India Company ships Belvedere and P. Douglas, circa 1800.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three horseshoes below a crest of a falcon's head in a ducal coronet and above the motto "On fear not" and monogram "PJF.", circa 1800 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Verso of a Chinese man and a village scene.
      Flanked on both sides by flowers.
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three horseshoes below a crest of a falcon's head in a ducal coronet and above the motto "On fear not" and monogram "PJF.", circa 1800 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three horseshoes below a crest of a falcon's head in a ducal coronet and above the motto "On fear not" and monogram "PJF.", circa 1800 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding an umbrella and a village scene.
  - Forbes family, Craigievar Castle, Aberdeenshire, Scotland
    - Round counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon with a cross pattee fitchee between three bears' heads couped below a crest of a cock proper and above the motto "Watch.", circa 1790-1830 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Verso has monogram "JAF."
  - Foulis family of Colinton, Edinburgh, Scotland
    Possibly Charles Foulis, captain of the East India Company ship Lord Anson.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with three laurel leaves below an emblem of a dexter hand couped and holding a sword on a torse, all below the motto, "Mente manuque praesto.", circa 1755 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Verso has floral pattern.
  - Gahagan family, Ireland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and crest of a greyhound passant on a torse and above a monogram "G.", circa 1800-1810 (Box 1, Folder 63)
      Verso of a Chinese man punching a bag.
  - Galbraith family, Scotland
    - Round counter with a geometric border and a crest of a boar's head erased on a torse and surrounded by motto "Ab obice saevior.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      Verso of a Chinese man.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and a crest of a boar's head erased on a torse and surrounded by motto "Ab obice saevior.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      Verso of a Chinese man and house.
  - Garioch family, Kinstair, Aberdeenshire, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a palm tree growing out of mount on a torse above the monogram "G" and flanked by flowers., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a staff and diapering.
  - Gillett family, Ipswich, Sussex, or Broadfiel, Norfolk, England
    - Round counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lucy's head erect, collared, and erased on a torse above the monogram "WEG.", circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lucy's head erect, collared, and erased on a torse above the monogram "WEG.", circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Gladstanes family
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-griffin holding in the dexter talon a sword on a torse above the motto "Fide et virtue," and flanked by a scene with a bird and a dog., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-griffin holding in the dexter talon a sword on a torse above the motto "Fide et virtue," and flanked by a scene with a bird and a fish., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 70)
      Verso of two Chinese boys, a Chinese woman, and a village scene.
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-griffin holding in the dexter talon a sword on a torse above the motto "Fide et virtue," and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Gordon-Mann family
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon with three boars' heads erased impaling three goats passant below a crest of a stag's head erased in a ducal crown., circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Gould family, Frampton, Glamorgan, Wales
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and an escutcheon with a lion rampant on a counterchanged saltire below a crest of an arm embowed, vested, cuffed, and holding in the hand a banner of six stripes and a canton with a cross., circa 1790-1830 (Box 1, Folder 73)
      Verso has a Chinese pagoda tower and building.
  - Gray family
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of an anchor on a torse below the motto "Anchor fast anchor," and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 74)
      Verso of three Chinese men and a village scene and applied red ink.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of an anchor on a torse below the motto "Anchor fast anchor," and flanked by a scene with two dogs., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Rectangle counter with deep carving an a floral border and a crest of an anchor on a torse below the motto Anchor fast anchor and flanked by a scene with a bird and a lion passant., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Gregory family, Stivichall, Warwickshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with five quarterings below a crest of a demi-boar rampant, collared, and crined on a torse above the motto "Vigilanter," and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 77)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one in a boat, and a village scene.
  - Grose family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a cat sejant on a torse above the monogram "TG.", circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 78)
      Verso has a basket with flowers.
  - Grose family, Richmond, Surrey (later London), England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and a crest of a paschal lamb passant and holding with its dexter foot the banner on a torse., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 79)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a sword.
  - Hall family, Grantham, Lincolnshire, England, or Sussex, England
    - Round counter with a key fret border and a crest of a talbot's head erased above the monogram "IRH.", circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 80)
      Verso of a moth and vine border and an escutcheon with three talbots' head erased above the motto "Silentio et spes."
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and a crest of a talbot's head erased above the monogram "IRH.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and a crest of a talbot's head erased above the monogram "IRH.", circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Harries family of Cruckton and Tong Castle, Shropshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a crest of a hawk preying on a pheasant with wings inverted on a torse., circa 1735 (Box 1, Folder 83)
      Verso has a heart.
  - Harrison family, Lancashire and Northamptonshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and an escutcheon of a cross with five pheons. Both sides flanked by flowers., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 84)
      Verso of a dexter arm embowed, purfled, and cuffed and holding a broken dart on a torse above a monogram "H."
  - Hewer family, Oxborough, Norfolk, England
    - Round counter with a line border and two talbots' heads between two flaunches., circa 1700-1770 (Box 1, Folder 85)
      Verso has a demi-dragon collared and lined with wings engorsed.
  - Hislop family, Tothill, Devon, England.
    Probably Sir Thomas Hislop, 1st Baronet, (1764-1843).
    - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a vine and moth border and a crest of a buck's head couped out of a mural coronet above the insignia of the Order of the Bath and flanked by a scene with two dogs., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Hobart family, Earl of Buckinghamshire, Hampden House, Buckinghamshire, England
    Possibly Robert Hobart (1760-1816), 4th Earl of Buckinghamshire, or George Robert Hobart-Hampden (1789-1849), 5th Earl of Buckinghamshire
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a bull passant above a earl crown and encircled with the motto "Auctor pretiosa facit.", circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 87)
      Verso has a Chinese man fishing.
  - Hughes family, Middleton Stoney, Oxfordshire, England
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a heron trussed on a torse above a monogram "Y," and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a heron trussed on a torse above a monogram "Y," and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 89)
      Verso of two Chinese men and a Chinese woman holding a fan and a village scene.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a heron trussed on a torse above a monogram Y and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Hyde family, Earl of Clarendon of Watford, Hertfordshire, England.
    Probably either Thomas Villiers, 1st Earl of Clarendon(1709-1786) or Thomas Villiers, 2nd Earl of Clarendon (1753-1824).
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three lozenges below a ducal crown., circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with an escutcheon with a chevron between three lozenges below a ducal crown., circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Isake or Izake family, Devon, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon a cross pattee between four lances below a crest of a hind on a horse., circa 1790-1830 (Box 1, Folder 93)
      Verso of a Chinese man fishing.
  - Johnstone family, Dumfries, Scotland
    - Shuttle counter with a geometric border and a crest of a winged spur on a torse., circa 1800-1810 (Box 1, Folder 94)
      Verso of a Chinese man dancing or performing martial arts.
  - Jones family, Monmouthshire, Wales
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a stag attired on a chapeau turned up., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 95)
      Verso of two Chinese men, one holding a sword.
  - Kekewich family, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a leopard's head and neck affrontée on a torse above a monogram "JSK.", circa 1790-1830 (Box 1, Folder 96)
      Verso of a Chinese woman with a fan.
  - Knott family, Sussex and London, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three crescents below a crest of a unicorn's head., circa 1765 (Box 1, Folder 97)
      Verso has a crest of a unicorn's head on a torse.
  - Lavie family, Béarn and Guyenne, France
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a eagle's head and neck couped on a torse and surrounded by the motto "Post funera vivo.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 98)
      Verso a monogram "JML."
  - Livingstone family, Earl of Linlithgow, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-savage holding a club in his dexter hand and round the sinister arm a serpent below the motto "Si je puis," and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Lowndes family, Winslow, Buckinghamshire, England.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and an escutcheon with fretty interlacings and a leopard's head erased below a crest of a leopard's head gorged with a laurel wreath on a torse., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Mainwaring family, Peover Superior (Over Peover), Cheshire, England
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of an ass's head out of a ducal crown on a torse and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 101)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one man carrying a yoke, and a village scene.
  - Maitland family, Earl of Lauderdale, Lauder, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lion sejant affrontée and ducally crowned, holding in the dexter paw a sword and the sinister paw a fleur-de-lis., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Mason family, Beel House, near Amersham, Buckinghamshire, England
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-lion rampant holding a crescent in a mural crown on a torse above monograms "JJM" and "AM" and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-lion rampant holding a crescent in a mural crown on a torse above monograms "JJM and AM" and flanked by a Chinese village scene., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Maule family, Parish of Panbride, Angus, Scotland
    Probably William Maule (1700-1782), 1st Earl Panmure.
    - Rectangle counter with a crest of a wyvern with two heads spouting fire above a coronet., circa 1744 (Box 1, Folder 105)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a crest of a wyvern with two heads spouting fire above a coronet., circa 1744 (Box 1, Folder 106)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a crest of a wyvern with two heads spouting fire above a coronet., circa 1744 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - McClintock family, Ireland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a fretted border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three escallops above the motto "Virtute et labore," and flanked by a scene with two crickets., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 108)
      Verso of a crest of a lion passant on a torse above a monogram "M" and flanked by a scene with two Chinese men.
  - McGregor family, Scotland
    - Rectangle counter with a fretted border and a crest of a lion's head erased proper crowned with an antique crown on a torse and surrounded by the motto "Ard cholle [sic].", circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - McMahon family, Ireland
    - Rectangle counter with a geometric border and crest of a sinister arm holding a sword impaling a fleur-de-lis on a torse above a monogram "DM.", circa 1800-1810 (Box 1, Folder 110)
      Verso of a Chinese man carrying a yoke with baskets of fish.
  - Morison family, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of three Saracen heads conjoined in one neck proper, their heads looking to the chief, dexter, and sinister on a torse and encircled by the motto "Pretio prudentia praestat.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Murray and Gray family, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with three stars in the center a heart impaling a lion rampant and in his dexter paw an anchor below a crest an olive branch on a torse above the motto "Ex bello quies.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 112)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a tray with a bowl.
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with three stars in the center a heart impaling a lion rampant and in his dexter paw an anchor below a crest an olive branch on a torse above the motto "Ex bello quies.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 113)
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with three stars in the center a heart impaling a lion rampant and in his dexter paw an anchor below a crest an olive branch on a torse above the motto "Ex bello quies.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 114)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a fan and a village scene.
  - Newenham family, Thenford, Northamptonshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a demi-lion rampant between two wings expanded on a torse and above the motto, "Deo averso leo vincitur.", circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Norris family, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a fretted border and a crest of a pelican feeding her young on a torse below the motto "Sic his qui diligunt," and above the monogram "CWN" and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 116)
      Verso of three Chinese men carrying yokes and a village scene.
  - Nourse family
    Probably John Nourse (died 1774) of Woodeaton, Oxfordshire, England, or John Norse (1755-1808), Weston under Penyard, Herefordshire, England.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of an arm vested and cuffed and the hand holding a snake entwined round the arm on a torse., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 117)
      Verso of a Chinese man, probably making noodles, and a village scene.
  - Oakes family
    Probably Hildebrand Oakes (1754-1822), 1st Baronet of the Oakes Baronetcy, of the Army, and the Oakes Baronets, of Hereford
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a reserves border and a crest of a stag's head and neck couped on a torse and above the initials "HO.", circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - Square counter with a reserves border and a crest of a stag's head and neck couped on a torse and above the initials "HO.", circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 119)
    - Round counter with a reserves border and a crest of a stag's head and neck couped on a torse and above the initials "HO.", circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Ogilvie and Grant family, Earl of Seafield, Scotland
    Probably Lewis Alexander Grant-Ogilvy (1767-1840), 5th Earl of Seafield
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a mountain in flames above a monogram "AG," surrounded by the motto "Craigellachie," and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1820 (Box 1, Folder 121)
      Verso of two Chinese men holding brushes, a Chinese woman holding a flower, and a village scene.
  - Ogilvie family, Earl of Findlater, Scotland
    Possibly Lady Mary Murray Ogilvy (1720-1775), the wife of James Ogilvy (1714-1770), 6th Earl of Findlater, 3rd Earl of Seafield
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a lion rampant holding in its paws a plummet below the motto, "Tout jour," and above the monogram "MO.", circa 1750 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Ogilvie family, Hartwoodmyres, near Selkirk, Selkirkshire, Scotland.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a talbot's head erased above a monogram "ALO" surrounded by the motto "Ad finem spero.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Ogilvie family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a lion's gamb erased on a torse above a monogram "HO.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 124)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a brush and a village scene.
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a lion's gamb erased on a torse above a monogram "HO.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 125)
      Verso of two Chinese men cooking and a village scene.
  - Palmer family, Great Yarmouth and Loddon, Norfolk, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-panther issuing flames from his ears and mouth holding a branch on a torse above the monogram "IP.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 126)
      Verso of a flowering branch.
      Both sides flanked with flowers.
  - Paxton family
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with two chevrons between three mullets below a crest of an eagle's head erased charged on the neck with two chevrons and between a pair of wings and above the motto "Pro fide et rege et lege," and flanked by a scene with two dogs., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Peers family of Chiselhampton, Oxfordshire, England.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a demi-griffin segreant wings addorsed on a torse., circa 1730 (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Perceval family, Earl of Egmont, Ireland
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon with three crosses pattée above a fess dancetty supported by two griffins below the crest of a thistle., circa 1700-1770 (Box 1, Folder 129)
      Probably the Countess of Egmont and Baroness Arden, Catherine Compton Perceval (1731-1784)
      Verso has the crest of a thistle.
    - Fish-shaped counter with a crest of a thistle leaved proper on a torse on both sides, circa 1720-1760 (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Perreau family, London, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a swags border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three leopards' heads., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 131)
      Verso has the monogram "RMP" below a crest of a leopard's head guardant and couped at the neck and out of a ducal crown.
  - Pitt family, Earl of Londonderry, Ireland
    Ownership attributed to Henrietta Pitt.
    - Round counter with a drilled and Queen Charlotte border and a monogram "H" below the motto "Amitié.", circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 132)
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled and Queen Charlotte border and a monogram "H" below the motto "Amitié.", circa 1790-1800 (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Proby and MacDonald family
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a fretted border and an escutcheon of a fess with a lion passant impaling first and fourth a dexter arm armored and holding a crosslet and second and third towers under a crest of an ostrich's head in a ducal crown and holding a key in its beak above motto "Manus haec inimica tyrannis," and flanked by a scene with two crickets., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 134)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one man hold a dog and another holding a yoke, and a village scene.
  - Proby family, Earl of Carysfort, Carysfort, Wicklow, Ireland
    Probably John Joshua Proby (1751-1828), 1st Earl of Carysfort
    - Round counter with a geometric border and a crest of an ostrich's head erased in a ducal crown holding a key in its beak on a torse., circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 135)
      Verso of a Chinese man carrying a flower in a pot.
  - Raper family, London or Yorkshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with counterchanged fesses and three dragons' heads erased., circa 1760-1770; 2 identical counters (Box 1, Folder 136-137)
  - Reyley and Foster families
    - Rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with a fess between three crosses formée fitchée impaling three buglehorn below a dragon's head erased and a helm., circa 1780-1810 (Box 1, Folder 138)
      Verso has monogram "ICR."
      The counter has four holes: two along both the upper and lower edges.
  - Richmond family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with a trident and sword in saltire in chief and a crowned serpent around a pillar below a crest of a trident and sword in saltire in a ducal crown, all above the motto "Fato prudentia major.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Richmond alias Webb family, Stewkley, Buckinghamshire, and Rodbourne Cheney in Swindon, Wiltshire, England
    - Square counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a tilting spear broken in three parts, one piece erect, the other two in saltire, enfiled with a ducal crown on a torse above an escutcheon with the monogram "C.", circa 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 140)